<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The religious impostor: or, The life of Alexander a sham-prophet, doctor and fortune-teller. Out of Lucian. Dedicated to Doctor S-lm-n, and the rest of the new religious fraternity of free-thinkers, near Leather-Sellers-Hall. By Sebastian Smith, Esq;</title>
            <author>Smith, Sebastian, b. 1677 or 8.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4207A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218093</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829719</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34162</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2002:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The religious impostor: or, The life of Alexander a sham-prophet, doctor and fortune-teller. Out of Lucian. Dedicated to Doctor S-lm-n, and the rest of the new religious fraternity of free-thinkers, near Leather-Sellers-Hall. By Sebastian Smith, Esq;</title>
                  <author>Smith, Sebastian, b. 1677 or 8.</author>
                  <author>Lucian, of Samosata. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the Company of the Saints of the New Stamp, in the first year of Grace, and free-thinking, and sold next door to the Devil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and publication date conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: Alexander: or, The false prophet. Out of Lucian.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf consists of verse headed: To the unknown translator, by a young married woman.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34162:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34162:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Religious Impoſtor: OR, THE LIFE OF Alexander, A <hi>Sham-Prophet, Doctor</hi> and <hi>Fortune-Teller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of LUCIAN.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to Doctor <hi>S—lm—n,</hi> and the reſt of the new Religious Fraternity of <hi>Free-Thinkers,</hi> near <hi>Leather-Sellers-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtian Smith,</hi> Eſq</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AMSTERDAM,</hi> Printed for the Company of the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>New Stamp,</hi> in the firſt Year of <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Free-Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and Sold next door to the <hi>Devil.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34162:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34162:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Worthy Doctor</hi> S—lm—n, <hi>and the Company of the Saints of the new Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> alias, <hi>The</hi> Free-Thinkers.</head>
            <p>I Have been long doubtful to whom the following Hiſtory ought to be Addreſs'd, but cannot find any one to whoſe Patronage it might ſo properly be recommended as Yours, Worthy Sir. And, indeed, the Analogy that is betwixt the Heroe of this Piece, and your ſelf, ſeems to challenge your Protection. For, were I a <hi>Pythagorean,</hi> I ſhould ſwear that our <hi>Alexander</hi> animated and inform'd your numerical lump of Clay, as ſure as ever <hi>Pythagoras</hi> himſelf was <hi>Homer,</hi> or <hi>Euphorbus;</hi> and that your Face was much more truly <hi>Braſs,</hi> than ever his Thigh was <hi>Gold.</hi> But let that paſs, thoſe Opinions are worn out long ſince, and nothing will ſatisfie this incredulous Age but demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; however, I ſhall unburthen my Conſcience to you and all the World, and let 'em ſee what reaſons I have for my Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This <hi>Alexander,</hi> when a Boy, was Apprentice to a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebank, under whom he ſerv'd as <hi>Whachum</hi> to his <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> and us'd to inveigle and divert the amazed ſilly Rout, with tumbling through a Hoop and Vaulting, and amuſe 'em with Tricks of <hi>Legerdemain,</hi> and <hi>Sleight of hand,</hi> conveying Money nimbly and dexterouſly out of the Spectators Purſes, Pockets, or Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, which his Maſter was to Conjure for, and reſtore for a Reward: He ſerv'd him likewiſe in ſeveral other Capacities; as, <hi>Jugler, Sub-Conjurer, Aſtrologer, Ganymede,</hi> and <hi>Orator,</hi> made <hi>Speeches,</hi> and wrote <hi>Panegyricks</hi> in praiſe of his Maſter's <hi>Panacea's, Panchymagogons, Family Pills</hi> and <hi>Powders, Cephalicks, Antipodugricks, Alexipharmacks, Antiſcorbuticks, Hyſtericks,</hi> and what not; He wrote <hi>Almanacks,</hi> to direct the taking of his Medicines, and made the Stars vouch for their Vertues, and was as well a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as breathing Diſpenſatory of his own Receipts: He Calculated <hi>Nativities, Told Fortunes,</hi> had admirable Secrets to <hi>Soddercrack'd Maidenheads,</hi> and incomparable <hi>Philtre</hi>'s for the Conſolation of <hi>Diſpairing Damſels.</hi> Beſides all this, which his Maſter ſhar'd with him, he had one Trade to himſelf, whoſe Revenue was his ſole
<pb facs="tcp:34162:3"/>Propriety, which was letting out his <hi>Poſtern</hi> (for he was a good ſmug young Rogue.) All this he did under his Maſter for an honeſt livelihood; but his Maſter dying, and the growth of his Beard, and decay of his Face, beginning to put the Counterpart out of Repute, he ſets up and ſucceeds him in his buſineſs, and a <hi>Quack</hi> he was for ſome time. But the Novelty of the Cheat being over, Trade began to grow dull, and the Scene muſt be ſhifted, ſo our Doctor packs up all, and away he marches, through ſeveral Countries he ſtrowled; but after all, the Profits ariſing from this courſe of Life were not ſufficient to ſatisfie his Ambition; ſo that ſome new Project muſt be ſtarted: In order to which, he aſſociates to himſelf a Fellow, whom he had in his Travels ſcrap'd acquaintance with; he was a kind of Medley, part <hi>Author,</hi> part <hi>Bookſeller,</hi> one that publiſhed and ſold his own Works, whom he obſerv'd to have an excellent knack of Canting and Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felting Religion, and to have cunning enough to Cheat his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. To this Man he imparts his deſign of ſetting up for a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> and invites him into the Partnerſhip of his Stratagem; and together theſe crafty Complotters ſet forward for <hi>Paphlagonia</hi> our Hero's Native Country, which they choſe for the Scene of their Actions, becauſe the Inhabitants were a ſort of ſtupid Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed People, of large Faith, and very little Senſe, eaſie and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous, Lovers of Novelty, and addicted to Superſtition. Here they put in execution their Plot, gave out Oracles for 12 <hi>d.</hi> a piece, and ſoon grew into mighty Reputation among theſe ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Gulls. What methods they took to bring their deſign to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, I need not inform you, who are already ſufficiently vers'd in all the meaſures requiſite for ſuch Undertakings.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie to apprehend for what end I give you this Summary of the Hiſtory of <hi>Alexander,</hi> whom I take to have been a Type of You: For your Parts have been no leſs exercis'd than his, Your Education and Profeſſion the ſame: If he made himſelf known to Foreign Countries, ſurely you have not ſate idle at home; the <hi>Church Yards</hi> and <hi>Burying-Places</hi> are every where ample Witneſſes of your Travels. If Statues were rais'd to his Memory, Millions of <hi>Graveſtones,</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>Marble</hi> and <hi>Braſs</hi> will perpetuate your Name. Was he free of his averſe <hi>Venery?</hi> You have been no niggard of your Talent on the other ſide, infinite numbers have taſted of your Benevolence, as well Siſters as others: You have Cultivated the neglected Soil, and by You the Barren has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Fruitful: You have Sowed where you have not Reaped,
<pb facs="tcp:34162:3"/>and Strew'd where you have not Gathered. All Climates and Conditions have reap'd the fruit of your Labour. You have been, as it were, the common Father, and have raiſed up Seed not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Faithful, but even to the Gentiles alſo, ſo extenſive has your Charity been. Was he beneficial to the World by his skill in Medicines? You have ſurpaſs'd him in that too, as far as the Subſtance does its Shadow: You teach when to cut Corns, and Let Blood: By you old Nurſes are inſtructed to make <hi>Carduus-Poſſets,</hi> and <hi>Chalybeat-Pancakes:</hi> Bawds to cauſe Abortions, and to propagate the <hi>Pox:</hi> Strumpets to counterfeit <hi>Maidenheads,</hi> and provoke <hi>Venery.</hi> In a word, your <hi>Diſpenſatories</hi> are ineſtimable Jewels in the publick Treaſury; there may be learn'd to Cure <hi>Scald Heads,</hi> the <hi>Itch, Corns, Chilblains,</hi> and <hi>Kib'd Heels,</hi> with many Secrets more of equal value. Nor are you inferiour to him in point of Prediction: For your <hi>Almanacks,</hi> and <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Chiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy,</hi> have made all the World Prophets: You can make the Stars depoſe whatever you pleaſe; and the very Lines of every Man's hand confirm what you ſay of him: You can tell at firſt ſight, <hi>That he that is born to be Hang'd ſhall never be Drown'd,</hi> and, <hi>That the Pope of</hi> Rome <hi>ſhall not be Lord Mayor next Year.</hi> But oh! the unhappy State of Merit! it is very rarely regarded, and truth is ſeldom credited; this <hi>Caſſandra</hi> experienc'd many Ages ago; and your repreſentative <hi>Alexander,</hi> for ſome time labour'd under. But he found means to ſurmount all the difficulties he met with; and the very ſame expedient relieves you. Religion was his <hi>Aſylum,</hi> and it is your Refuge; it was his Stalking Horſe, and is your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coy. Well, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſpeed you in your Deſign, 'tis a Pious Project, and may your Succeſs be as much greater than his, as your Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe is more difficult and hazardous: His Scene was a Country of Sots, and his Auditors a parcel of Fools, ready gather'd and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to his hand: Yours is an intelligent and populous City, and your Cullies muſt be pick'd and broken to your uſe, by your own Induſtry and Cunning. 'Tis true indeed your Inſtruments and Methods are the ſame, but there is a vaſt diſparity in the matter to be wrought upon. He anſwer'd all Queſtions, ſo do you: He propos'd Remedies for all ſorts of Grievances, ſo do you: He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd Phyſick, ſo do you: He us'd the aſſiſtance of a crafty Fellow, ſo do you. Only he met with no oppoſition, all believ'd him, ſo they do not you. However, proceed, let your Courage carry you through all Obſtacles, and your Conſcience be your Comfort: You know the old ſaying, <hi>Non ſit ſine periculo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Faint Heart
<pb facs="tcp:34162:4"/>never won Fain Lady.</hi> It is no eaſie matter to found a new Church, <hi>Paul</hi>'s, you ſee can't be built in a day. But great will be the Honour when the Feat is done, adding one point to our Faith, is adding to the compaſs by which we ſteer to Heaven, our Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are the more exact. Go on, regulate the whole Compaſs, and be your ſelf the needle to point out the way. None but evil-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men can think our Spiritual Navigation ſufficiently improv'd: I think he that finds out a ſhorter cut to Heaven, is a greater Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor to Mankind, and deſerves more Honour than if he found the <hi>North Eaſt</hi> Paſſage to the <hi>Indies.</hi> Who would wait a tedious Paſſage by a Waggon, who might go by the <hi>Penny-Poſt.</hi> Correct the Geography of Religion, and ſhew us a better Map of the Roads to the next World. Outdo <hi>Bunyan,</hi> and all the Spiritual <hi>Choro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers</hi> that have gone before you. Oh how happy you whoſe Souls have been anointed and tarr'd all over with his Doctrine, and liquor'd like Carriers Boots, to take off the Scabs of Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; Whoſe <hi>Scirrhous Conſciences</hi> have been ſoften'd by an <hi>Emolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cataplaſme</hi> of Argument? Who have taken an Emetick Doſe of <hi>Repentance,</hi> and the <hi>Cathartick Pills</hi> of <hi>Contrition?</hi> Who have pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently endur'd a <hi>Diaphoretick Dialogue,</hi> and whoſe Concupiſcence has been <hi>Flux'd</hi> and <hi>Salivated</hi> by the <hi>Precipitate</hi> of <hi>Spiritual Admonition,</hi> whoſe Appetites have been rais'd by a <hi>Stomachick Whet</hi> of <hi>Pious Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity,</hi> and ſatisfied with a Meal of <hi>Ghoſtly Comfort?</hi> Whoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits have been rais'd by the dear <hi>Cordial</hi> of <hi>Zeal,</hi> and whoſe ſtrength ſupported by the precious <hi>Aliment</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Carnal Itches</hi> have been kill'd by the <hi>Unguent</hi> of <hi>Mortification,</hi> and whoſe inward Aches have been taken off by the <hi>Opiate</hi> of <hi>Election.</hi> To recount here the infinite advantages you, who are his Diſciples, have by this <hi>Phyſician Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal,</hi> were too tedious at this time, ſince what is paſt muſt make all the World as well envious as ſenſible of your Happineſs. I ſhall conclude with a ſmall Requeſt to your great Maſter. In a word then, Pious Sir, May you never ceaſe to hold forth the <hi>Sucking Bottle</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to the <hi>Babes</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Crutches of Faith</hi> to the <hi>Crippled Saint.</hi> Satisfie the craving <hi>Siſter,</hi> and aſſiſt the impotent <hi>Brother;</hi> ſo may your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of the <hi>Weather</hi> always hold good, and your, <hi>Almanack</hi> be fill'd with Saints of your own <hi>Cannonizing,</hi> which is the Prayer of, Pious Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Devout Admirer, Sebaſtian Smith.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:34162:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Reader is deſired to take notice that the Tranſlator has not tied himſelf to a Literal Verſion, but contented himſelf barely to give him the full Subſtance of the Hiſtory, which he hopes he has not wrong'd, either by adding or ſubſtracting any thing material: He has taken a larger Liberty with the Oracles, ſome of which he hath omitted, and given a new turn to the reſt; as thinking them to contain nothing that might either Inform or Divert the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reader: In the whole he hath chiefly follow'd the Example of Monſieur <hi>Abancourt,</hi> whoſe Verſion is to be found in Dr. <hi>Spon's Recherches cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieuſes del Antiquité.</hi> But beſides, the Worthy Doctor, who had the Honour of our Epiſtle Dedicatory, there are Two more of the Gang, whoſe Characters follow. One of theſe Spiritual Navigators, a weak help to the new-founded Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umvirate, aſſiſted his Two Brethren to facilitate their Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, by finding out the ſhorteſt Paſſage to their Wits end, and that is no far Journey you'll ſay. He is a great Friend to the Crooked Bodice-Seller in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> and Counſeller in Ordinary to his long-noſed Madam. This wonderful <hi>Caco-Coxcomb,</hi> call'd ſo not from the Greek, but from the good luck of beſhitting himſelf, in a Conflict with a ſurely Low-Country Captain, who happen'd to have more Brawn than the other had Brain to prevent (like
<pb facs="tcp:34162:5"/>
               <hi>Pen</hi>) any farther Quarrels, though good to turn Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſt. This Learned <hi>Juris-concealer</hi> was, to ever bleſſed Remembrance, born a Gooſe and bred a Gown-man, ſo no ſwap in the changing of his Trade, and a Divine Quaker has well obſerved in his Poem, called the <hi>Blockhead's Blockade.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Bitching ſtill the Sot affected change.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtant to nothing but a Dunce's Brains;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tho' his ill face and worſer ills applied,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Makes me believe a roguiſh Poet lied.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>And ſo in <hi>Dad</hi> I have done with Father <hi>D——dly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other is an Honeſt Man, of ſome Learning, and a great deal of miſtaken Zeal, drawn in to be their <hi>Apollo,</hi> but he ſoon found that the other Legs of the Cricket were not in proportion to his Strength, and ſo that Oracle ceaſed, ſpoiling a good old Proverb in the fall; not between two Stools, but a Seat of one Leg, the Arſe of two Thirds of the Learned Triumvirate went to the Ground.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="story">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34162:5"/>
            <head>ALEXANDER: OR, The Falſe Prophet.</head>
            <head type="sub">Out of <hi>Lucian.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOU impoſed no ſmall task upon me, my dear <hi>Celſus,</hi> when you enjoyned me to write the Life of <hi>Alexander</hi> the pretended Son of <hi>Poda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lirius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">For ſo he called himſelf.</note> which for variety of incidents, is no leſs famous than that of his Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> ſince the latter has not ſignalized himſelf more by his Noble Exploits than the former has done by his well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>managed Impoſtures. However, out of Compliance with you, I undertake it, and will endeavour to acquit my ſelf of the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance as well as I can, provided that you carry a ſtock of good Nature about you to ſupply my Defects, and pardon my Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. At the ſame time, I am not without my apprehenſions, that the World will be apt to condemn both of us; me for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing ſo many Villianies, and you for putting your Friend upon the Imployment: For tho' the Hero of our <hi>Drama</hi> juſtly deſerved to have his Carcaſs torn in pieces by Beaſts of his own Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet few Perſons will be ſo complaiſant to his Memory, as to think he deſerves to have his Name recorded in Hiſtory. But if any one ſhall Attack me upon this Article, I will e'en defend my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34162:6"/>ſelf by the example of <hi>Arrius,</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>Epictetus,</hi> who thought it not below his Learning or Quality to oblige Poſterity with the Hiſtory of a Famous Robber.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>As lately one of the greateſt Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has condeſcended to write the Life of</hi> Et caetera Young.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Behold then, after ſo authentick a Preſident, the Life of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Ravager, not one who made Mountains and Foreſts the ſolitary Scene of his Actions, but Towns and Cities, and did not over-run Deſarts, but ravaged a whole Empire. To begin with his Deſcription: He was of a good Shape and Mien, a lively Eye, his Complexion black, a clear Voice, a ſweet and affable Tone, with a little thin Beard, and ſome falſe Hair ſo dexterouſly mext with his own, that one could not eaſily diſtinguiſh them.
<note place="margin">So was Mahomet, and ſo were moſt of the new Religion-Founders; for without that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could never h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with their beſt Clients the Women.</note>Beſides this, he was furniſhed with ſeveral good Qualities, quick Apprehenſion, a tenacious Memory, a great Vivacity of Thought, but theſe Talents he wholly Conſecrated to Miſchief, and made no other uſe of them than to raiſe him above all thoſe Impoſtors of curſed Memory, that ever viſited the World. He never ſhew'd a geain of Modeſty but once, and that was in a Letter to his Son-in-law <hi>Rutilianus,</hi> wherein he compared himſelf with a great deal of Self denial to <hi>Pythagoras:</hi> But, with <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s leave be it ſpoken, if <hi>Pythagoras</hi> had lived in his Time, he had been but a Pigmy to our Gyant: Not that I wou'd in the leaſt compare that Philoſopher to ſuch a profligate Raſcal; but only obſerve, That all that's falſely faid of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> is not to be named the ſame Year with what is really true of our <hi>Alexander.</hi> In ſhort, before you proceed any farther, imagine to your ſelf an abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſorts of Cheats, Lyes, Perjuries, and Impoſtures, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a ſprightly bold deſigning Spirit, and carried on by a Perſon who had the knack of making People believe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he pleaſed, but ſo reſerved and cautious, that no body ever parted from him but with this Opinion, That he was certainly one of the Honeſteſt, Godlieſt Men in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Education.</note>Being, as we have deſcribed him before, very handſome in his Youth, but miſerably Poor; he was obliged, in his own defence, to proſtitute
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34162:6"/>himſelf to all ſorts of Cuſtomers, and particularly to a certain <hi>Charlatan</hi> or <hi>Quack</hi> that ſet up for a Conjurer, ſold <hi>Charms</hi> and <hi>Philtres,</hi> cut <hi>Corns</hi> at the full of the Moon, <hi>Calculated Nativities,</hi> helped People to ſtoln <hi>Silver Spoons,</hi> and cou'd do a thouſand things of the like nature and importance. I muſt <hi>(en paſſant)</hi> do the Fellow ſo much Juſtice as to own he was ſomewhat skill'd in <hi>Phyſick;</hi> and that he knew ſeveral Receipts, ſome good and ſome bad; which is no wonder, for he was one of <hi>Apollonius Tyanaeus</hi>'s Countrymen, and was no Stranger to his Perſon. You ſee what a bleſſed Country our <hi>Quack</hi> had his Education in, and hence may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture that he was no little <hi>Scoundrel,</hi> but a <hi>Raſcal</hi> of good Figure and Addreſs.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>As Notorious an Impoſtor as our</hi> Alexander.</note> He obſerving the quick lively Spirit of our young <hi>Alexander,</hi> took a great deal of Pleaſure in Inſtructing him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as much taken with the Boy's Beauty, as the Boy was with his Maſter's dextrous way of living, who, in a ſhort time, of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple made him his Companion: By that time <hi>Alexander</hi> was grown up to Man's Eſtate, his Tutor and his Face were gone the way of all Tutors and Faces; in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> his Tutor was dead, and his Beauty was gone, ſo his Neceſſities drove him to find out ſome new extraordinary Project, whereby he might be in a capacity to keep Body and Soul together.</p>
            <p>In his Travels he pick'd up a Penny Chronicle-Writer of <hi>Byzantium,</hi> one of them, whom in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Language we call a Son of <hi>Grub-ſtreet,</hi> one that was a ſtedfaſt hardened impenitent Rogue.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He took one</hi> Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conas <hi>for his Companion.</hi>
               </note> Theſe two, after ſome Oath of Secrelie on both ſides, beat the Hoof together, and as they marched, Cheated a World of poor ignorant ſilly People, that had the Misfortune to fall into their Clutches. At laſt they dropt into the Acquaintance of an old Gentlewoman who had two commendable Qualities; for firſt ſhe had ſtore of Old Gold by her; and ſecondly, was of a Temper eaſie to be impoſed upon. She was born at <hi>Pella,</hi> formerly the Capital City of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> now in a manner a Deſart, and only Inhabited by a few ſorry Mechanicks, our two Sparks follow'd her from <hi>Bithynia</hi> to this place, eating and drinking all the while at her Expence; for why ſhould the Godly Starve, and the Rich only Riot? Being arrived here, and obſerving a ſort of large Serpents, ſo exceeding tame that they would kiſs the Women,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34162:7"/>nay, ſuck their Breaſts, and play with the Children without doing them any Miſchief (from whence undoubtedly came the Story of <hi>Olympias</hi>) they bought one, the biggeſt and the moſt beautiful they could find, and with no other Stock than this ſame Animal, and their own aſſurance, managed all the ſtrange adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures I am going to relate.
<note place="margin">Who pretended to have been obliged (the Ladies know my meaning) by a Serpent.</note> Theſe two bleſſed Rake-hells (I beg their Pardon, I ſhould call them Philoſophers) obſerving that Hope and Fear are the two Poles upon which Mankind turns; and indeed the whole Foundation of Curioſity and Superſtition, were reſolved to make both theſe Paſſions further their Ambitious Deſigns, and ſo ſet up an Oracle, which met with a ſucceſs infinitely above their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It was ſome time before they could pitch upon a place where to begin the Farce. <hi>Cocconas</hi> looked upon the City of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> to be the propereſt place for their deſign, becauſe of the mighty confluence there of the ſeveral Nations that lay around it: But <hi>Alexander</hi> preferr'd his own Country, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for his reaſon, the great Stupidity and Superſtition of the People, (both which you know are very neceſſary towards the eſtabliſhment of a new Religion) who no ſooner hear of a new upſtart Mountebank, but they meet him with beating of Drums, with Flutes and Cymbals; and in ſhort, Worſhip him as heartily as if they had ſeen him drop out of the Clouds.</p>
            <p>This advice being, after ſome debate reſolved upon, they pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately hid a Copper-Plate in the old Temple of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> whereon was written, <hi>That</hi> Aeſculapius <hi>with his Father</hi> Apollo, <hi>wou'd ſhortly come and fix his Habitation at</hi> Abonoteichos.
<note place="margin">That was the Cities Name where our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor was born.</note> After this, they ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived matters, that the Plate was found bearing this wonderful Inſcription, the news whereof immediately ſpread it ſelf through all <hi>Pontus, Bithynia,</hi> and particularly alarm'd the Town above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named; ſo that the Godly Inhabitants, in one of their publick Meetings, decreed a Temple to theſe Gods, and began to lay the Foundation of it. All this while <hi>Cocconas</hi> turned the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by retailing falſe and ambiguous Oracles at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> but unhappily died in one of his D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Debauches;
<note place="margin">Cocconas <hi>dies.</hi>
               </note> and ſoon after <hi>Alexander</hi> ſucceeds
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34162:7"/>him in his Function, with his Hair ſpread at full length about his Shoulders, a Veſt of Purple, bordered with White, over all this a Surplice, and in theſe Formalities pretended to Preach the Will of Heaven to the People. The wretched <hi>Paphlagonians,</hi> altho' they very well knew both his Father and Mother, who were kept by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; yet for all that were ſuch incredible Sots as to believe a Lying Oracle, publiſhed by our Impoſtor, in which he called himſelf the Son of <hi>Podalirius,</hi> who muſt certainly have been put to very hard ſhifts for want of a Bedfellow, if he were forced to come from <hi>Trica</hi> as far as <hi>Paphlagonia,</hi> to lie with this Juggler's Mother.</p>
            <p>He ſhamm'd another Oracle upon the People, under the name of one of the <hi>Sybill</hi>'s, wherein he talked of a <hi>Deliverer</hi> or <hi>Reſtorer,</hi> who was ſpeedily to appear; but all this was diſguiſed in ſuch a myſtical Jargon, that tho' nothing cou'd be made of it, yet the People fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied ſome deep Myſtery lay at the bottom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> therefore coming into his own Country, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe Predictions, you may ſwear he was followed and reſpected, and entertained like any God.
<note place="margin">His Reception when he came to his own Country.</note> He feigned himſelf ſometimes to be poſſeſſed with a Divine Fury, and by the means of the Root of a certain Herb, commonly called <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Herb, which he chaw'd (as Modern Sir <hi>Davy Dunce,</hi> in the Play, does his Tobacco) he wou'd foam exceſſively at the Mouth, which theſe ignorant Blockheads attributed to the force of the God that poſſeſſed him. He had not long before dreſſed up a Dragon's Head made of Linen Clouts, very much reſembling a Mans Face, which was taught to open and ſhut its Mouth, by the means of ſome Horſe-Hairs. Now this was to act in Concert with the Serpent above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, which was to ſuſtain the principal part in the Comedy. A little before he began the Show, he ſlily conveyed himſelf to the place where the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Temple were a laying, and meeting with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34162:8"/>a puddle of Water, he hid a Gooſe Egg in it, wherein he had incloſed a young Serpent that was but newly hatched.</p>
            <p>Next Morning he came all naked to the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, ſaving that he wore a Scarf with a Gold Fringe about his Waſt, to cover his Nudities, holding an Axe in his hand, and throwing his Hair about his Shoulder, as the Prieſts of <hi>Cybele</hi> are uſed to do. Then mounting upon a high Altar, he began to tell the Mob, how happy the City was in being honoured with the Birth of a God.</p>
            <p>At theſe words, all the People, who had left their Houſes to behold ſo ſurpriſing a Spectacle, fell a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Vow-making like ſtark mad, while our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Raſcal was bantering them in <hi>Hebrew</hi> or <hi>Phoenician,</hi> which almoſt ſcared them out of the little remainder of their Wits. At laſt he runs to the place where he had hid his Gooſe Egg, and entring the Water begins a <hi>Te Deum</hi> to <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> humbly beſeeching the latter to deſcend and ſhow himſelf to Men.
<note place="margin">Aeſculapius, <hi>the God of Medicine was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, under the ſhape of a Serpent, with a human Head, as appears by ſeveral Medals, and a Baſs-relief ſtill extant.</hi>
               </note> Theſe words were no ſooner pronounced, but he ſtrikes the Water with his Wand, and takes out the myſterious Egg, which had a God incloſed in its Shell; and having it now in his hand, he aſſures 'em that <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> was come. Every one was attentive to contemplate this pretty Myſtery, when our Impoſtor breaking the Egg-ſhell, lo! out comes the little Serpent I told you of before, and turned and wound himſelf nimbly round his Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <p>'Tis impoſſible to deſcribe the admiration and joy of the multitude at this wonderful fight: The Skye was filled with Acclamations, Praiſes, and Thanksgiving: One fell down on his Marrow-bones, and begs the God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34162:8"/>to reſtore him his Health; a ſecond prays to be an Alderman; a third to bury his Wife with all ſpeed; and ſo on, as their ſeveral Inclinations led them.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, our Holy Prophet runs home as hard as he cou'd drive, holding this new riggling Divinity in his hands, and follow'd by an infinite preſs of People, of all Ages and Conditions, who were tranſported out of their Wits, to think that a God was ſo kind as to come and take up his Quarters among them.</p>
            <p>He locked himſelf up in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, till his God, meaning the Serpent, had arrived to his juſt length and proportion; and one day, when the <hi>tag rag and long tail</hi> of <hi>Paphlagonia</hi> was got there, and his Houſe crammed with People from the Cellar up to the Garret; he ſeated himſelf on his Bed in his Prophetick Habit, and holding that great Serpent in his Boſom, which he had brought with him out of <hi>Macedonia;</hi> he began to ſhow him twining about his Neck, and drawing his long Tail after him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He publickly ſhows the Serpent, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was</hi> Aeſcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius <hi>himſelf.</hi>
               </note> But he purpoſely hid his Head under his Arm-pits, ſhewing only the Linnen head, which ſomewhat reſembled that of a Man; ſo that the Spectators were filled with the greateſt ſurprize imaginable.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34162:9"/>
            <p>We muſt here remark, That the Chamber was ſomewhat dark, and that the Company was principally compoſed of poor ſenſeleſs Ideots, who were already Cheated out of their little ſenſe and reaſon by the gibberiſh and illuſions of this Holy Counterfeit. To this we may add, that they did not ſtay long enough to diſcover the Cheat, but that as they entered at one door, ſo they went out at another immediately, to make way for the mighty throng of People that came in perpetually.</p>
            <p>This Spectacle continued for ſome days with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion; and afterwards was renewed as often as any Perſon of Quality arrived in thoſe Parts.</p>
            <p>We are not therefore to wonder, if the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid ignorant Mob ſwallowed his Miracles with ſo much alacrity, ſince even thoſe of better underſtandings could not tell what to think, when they ſaw and touched a Dragon, who was the other day hatched before their Eyes, grown on a ſuddain to ſuch a prodigious Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and what was the greateſt Riddle of all, having the Face of a Man.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34162:9"/>
            <p>An <hi>Epicurus,</hi> or a <hi>Democritus,</hi> or, in ſhort, any of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Philoſophers, who were well verſed in nature, would without any difficulty have pronounced it to be a juggle at firſt ſight, altho they could not diſcover the myſtery of the operation: But as all people have not the luck to be Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, the Inhabitants of <hi>Bythinia, Galatia,</hi> and <hi>Thrace</hi> went in ſhoals to ſatisfie their eye-ſight with thoſe Miracles, of which Fame had already made ſuch prodigious relations.
<note place="margin">Having eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation amongſt the People be ſets up an Oracle.</note> His Picture was ſold every where, with Statues of Silver and Copper, after the life. Nay, an Oracle was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which foretold his name, and ſtiled him, Glycon, <hi>the third of the race of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>who brought light to men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">By himſelf to be ſure.</note> So then our Impoſtor finding a favourable opportunity for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſets up for an Oracle-monger, and ſells his Predictions for Money; following the example of <hi>Amphilochus,</hi> who after the death of his father <hi>Amphiaraus,</hi> being ejected out of <hi>Thebes,</hi> withdrew into <hi>Aſia,</hi> where he told the <hi>Barbarians</hi> their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune for two-pence apiece.
<note place="margin">No Penny, no Oracle.</note>To bring this about, he in forms the people that the God was inclined to anſwer all manner of queſtions himſelf at ſuch an appointed time; and that they ſhould write down whatever they demanded a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution for, in a Letter ſealed up.
<note place="margin">Cheap enough of all conſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> Then ſhutting himſelf in, the Sanctuary of the Temple, which by this time was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, he cauſed all thoſe perſons who had given in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be called in order one after another, and there to have 'em reſtored to them again ſealed up as they were at firſt, with the Gods anſwer. It would have been an eaſie matter for a man of a tolerable capacity to have found out the Cheat, but theſe Sots did not perceive that he unſealed the Letters in private, and after he had incloſed what anſwer ſeem'd fitteſt for him, returned them back to their reſpective own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſealed exactly as at firſt. For there are an hundred ways of breaking open a Letter, without doing any injury to the Impreſſion; and I ſhall here ſet down one or two of them, that ſo for the future meer ſlight of hand may not paſs for a Miracle. In the firſt place, one may with a hot Needle disjoin the Wax that faſtens the Thread to the Letter, and not do the leaſt damage to the Seal, ſo that after he has read as much as he-pleaſes, he may rejoyn it as it was before.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>That was the old way. Hence the Phraſe</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num incidere, <hi>to break open a Letter.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34162:10"/>There is likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>other invention, which is as follows: The party takes Lime and Glue; or elſe a Maſtic compoſed of Pitch, Wax, and Bitumen, mingled with the powder of a very tranſparent Stone. Of theſe ingredients he makes a Ball, upon which, when it is as yet ſoft and tender, he takes the impreſſion of the Seal, after he has gently rubb'd it with Oyl or Hogs-greaſe: for it hardens in a moment, and will ſerve to ſeal the Letter again full as well as the very Seal. There are ſeveral other Secrets of the like nature, my dear friend, which it is not neceſſary for me to acquaint you with, ſince you have made mention of them in your Treatiſe of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice of the Magicians,</hi> which is an excellent Book, and very ſerviceable to undeceive thoſe ignorant people, who are ſo apt to be abuſed by their own credulity. But to re-aſſume our ſtory.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſet up for himſelf, he uſed the greateſt addreſs and dexterity he was maſter of, for fear of being found out in his Roguery;
<note place="margin">His caution in telling of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</note> and to that end always entrenched himſelf behind obſcure and ambiguous anſwers, according to the cuſtom of all Oracle-mongers. One while he encouraged, and at another time diſſwaded people from ſuch and ſuch enterprizes, as he ſaw moſt convenient: Sometimes he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed certain Remedies, or a courſe of Phyſick to the fick; for to give him his due, he knew ſeveral pretty Secrets in that Science. As for what related to ſucceſſions and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, he ever took care to delay his anſwers to ſuch queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, referring them to a better opportunity, or till his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet was in humour; for this impudent Viſionary always perſonated the God, and ſpoke in his name. His price was about 12 pence for every Oracle, which amounted to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ſum, for he retailed threeſcore or fourſcore thouſand of them in a year. Nor are we to wonder at it, for the people were ſo beſotted with theſe fooleries, (as 'tis the nature of the two legg'd herd to run after novelties, and be inquiſitive of future things) that the ſame perſon made ſometimes a dozen or fifteen demands, at twelve pence apiece for each of them; for it was not allowed them to put up two in the ſame Billet. But all the Money he received did not go immediately to his own Coffers, for he maintained abundance of Officers under him, ſome of whom put the Oracles into Verſe, others ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34162:10"/>them, or ſealed them, or interpreted them, or kept them; and every one had a Salary proportionable to his place and merits.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, he had his Spys and Emiſſaries in the remoteſt Countries, who ſpread the reputation of his Oracle in all places, aſſuring the people that it foretold things to come, diſcovered hidden treaſures, helped the right owners to what they had loſt, healed the ſick, and in fine did ten times more than can be expected.
<note place="margin">No Cheat to be carried on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſſiſtance.</note> Multitudes flocked to him from all parts with ſacrifices and preſents, as well for the God, as for the Prophet; for in one of his Oracles he commanded them to be kind to his Miniſter, as having little need of their Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings himſelf. No ſooner had ſeveral men of Worth and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcovered the deceit, and particularly ſome Philoſophers of <hi>Epicurus</hi>'s ſect, but he endeavored all he could to affright 'em, crying aloud that all the Country was over-run with Chriſtians and impious Perſons, who raiſed Calumnies againſt him, and commanded the People to ſtone them, if they had a mind to ingratiate themſelves with the God.
<note place="margin">This has been the artifice of corrupt Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in all Ages and Countries, to ſet the Mobb upon the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers of their wicked deſigns and ſo to have them knocked in the head for Gods ſake.</note> Being once demanded, how it fared with <hi>Epicurus</hi> in the other world, he replied, that he was duckt over Head and Ears in a naſty Puddle, and loaded with Chains of Lead. The reaſon is plain, he owed him a ſpight for laying open all theſe Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Impoſtures, that walk up and down the world, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of Religion: But <hi>Plato, Chryſippus</hi> and <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> were his good Friends. He had a particular averſion to the City of <hi>Amaſtris</hi> upon the account of ſome of <hi>Lepidus</hi>'s acquaintance there, as alſo of ſeveral <hi>Epicurean</hi> Philoſophers, and would never return an anſwer from his Oracle to any of its Inhabitants. But happening once to return one to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul's brother there, he made but a mock of him, ordering him to take a Hogs foot and ſome Mallows, for a pain in his ſtomach, and that in ſuch ridiculous terms that no body could tell what he meant. Whether it were becauſe he had none of his Officers at that inſtance near him to compoſe the Oracle, or becauſe he could not tell what anſwer to make.</p>
            <p>In the mean time he frequently ſhowed the Serpent to thoſe that had a mind to ſee him, but he ſtill kept the head of it in his own boſom, and would not permit them to touch any part of it but his body and his tail. Having a deſign one day
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34162:11"/>to improve his impoſture, he told them that <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> would anſwer viſibly, and this he called <hi>Anſwers from the Gods own mouth.</hi> He effected this by the help of a Cranes ſinews, dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly placed in the Dragons head which was made of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, and ſerved in ſtead of Organs to carry the voice of a man, who ſtood in the next room; but this Trick was not to be ſhown every day, and was principally calculated for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Condition. The anſwer he made to <hi>Severian,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the enterprize of <hi>Armenia,</hi> was of this number: in which he promiſed him Victory, but after his Defeat, he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted another in the room of it, which ſeemed to diſſwade him from this attempt. The truth on't is, he had impudence enough to correct his Oracles, when they did not ſucceeed, and if it ſo fell out that he promiſed health to a ſick party who afterwards happened to dye, he publiſhed another quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the former.</p>
            <p>However to gain the good graces of the Brotherhood, as <hi>Mallus, Claros</hi> and <hi>Didyma,</hi> where their Oracles told full as many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es as his own, he frequently commanded his Queriſts to conſult them, but eſpecially when he was hard put to it, and had a mind to evade a pinching Queſtion.
<note place="margin">Rogues will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways collogue with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Thus I have told you what paſſed in thoſe places that were near his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but when once his Reputation was ſpread in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> every one almoſt either viſited or ſent to him and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly men of the firſt Rank, and ſuch as were intereſted in their Prince's favour. The chief of theſe was <hi>Rutilianus,</hi> who had ſignalized himſelf on ſeveral occaſions, and was a very honeſt Gentleman, but ſo exceſſively ſuperſtitious that he could not for bear kneeling before all the ſtones he met on the road, upon which any effuſion had been made, or a Garland placed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>This was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently practiſed by the devouter ſort of Pagans, as we may ſee at the beginning of</hi> Minutius Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix.</note> He was once in a mind to quit the Army, which he commanded at that time, to make our Impoſtor a viſit at his own houſe, but upon ſecond conſiderations, diſpatched Meſſengers upon Meſſengers thither. As the perſons he ſent were only Varlets, it was no difficult matter to deceive them, and theſe Blockheads ſtill adding new lies to thoſe which their Fellows told before them, in order to make their relations the more agreeable, it increaſed his paſſion, and gave new vigor to his curioſity.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34162:11"/>
            <p>In the mean time being acquainted with moſt of the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Perſons of <hi>Rome,</hi> he recounted to them all that had been reported to him, and as the cuſtom of the world is, mingled ſomething of his own invention, to make the Legend more entertaining.
<note place="margin">Rutilianus <hi>helps to carry on the cheat.</hi>
               </note> So that he fill'd the whole Town with theſe Impoſtures, and engaged abundance of his friends to conſult the Oracle to know their fortune. They were very kindly received by our Prophet, who made them ſeveral Preſents, that at their return they might ſpeak well of him, and publiſh his praiſe. He made uſe of another trick, and that was this; if after he had peruſed their queſtions, he found ſome of them too bold, he kept the Billet without returning any anſwer to it, to have it as a pledge for the fidelity of the perſon that ſent it; who by this means was conſtrained to keep fair with this Raſcal, inſtead of complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him.</p>
            <p>And here I have a fit opportunity to recount to you ſome of the Anſwers he made to <hi>Rutilianus.</hi> This Nobleman having demanded of him, What ſort of Maſter he ſhould place over his Son? he anſwered, in ambiguous terms, as your Raſcally Oracles have always uſed to do, <hi>Pythagoras and Homer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A true Church trick for they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally reſerve a loop-hole for themſelves to creep out of.</note> But the Child dying ſome time after this, and our Fortune-teller being in ſome pain how to defend his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, <hi>Rutilianus</hi> help'd to put the Cheat upon himſelf, and gave out that he had foretold the death of his Son, in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning him for his Maſters thoſe that were out of the World. At another time the ſame Nobleman having asked him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the doctrine of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> what he had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was what he is now, and laſtly, what would become of him hereafter? He told him that he had been <hi>Achilles,</hi> then <hi>Menander,</hi> and that he would become a ray of the Sun after he had lived a hundred and fourſcore years. But for all that he died of Melancholy at the Age of ſeventy, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the direct promiſe of the Oracle, altho' it ſeemed to be one of the moſt authentic it ever uttered. <hi>Rutilianus</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining thoughts of a ſecond Marriage, our Prophet offered him his Daughter, whom he pretended to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Moon who fell in Love with him, as ſhe did in the days of <hi>Yore</hi> with <hi>Endimion,</hi> and commanded him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34162:12"/>to marry her. All which he did without any farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, after he had offered ſome Hecatombs to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law, and thought himſelf already made free of Heaven.</p>
            <p>After this mighty ſucceſs, our Impoſtor fell upon higher deſigns, and diſpatched Meſſengers into all Countries with his Oracles, admoniſhing ſome Cities to preſerve themſelves from Plagues, ſome from Fire, and others from Earthquakes; with a promiſe to ſend them effectual Remedies, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all theſe diſmal accidents.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A Quack this laſt year in</hi> Barkſhire <hi>ſold Pills to the Country People to preſerve them from Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes.</hi>
               </note> He likewiſe publiſhed an Oracle, as if it had immediately proceeded from the God's own mouth, to ſerve as a preſervative againſt a Contagion which then raged with extreme violence. One might have ſeen it written on the doors of moſt Houſes, being ſuppoſed to be a Soveraign remedy againſt this calamitous diſtemper; but by misfortune theſe Houſes were firſt viſited with it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe out of a vain confidence or ſecurity they neglected their own preſervation.</p>
            <p>He had ſeveral Setters at <hi>Rome,</hi> who acquainted him with the humour and inclination of all the great men there; and ſent him before-hand all the Queſtions they intended to ask him when they arrived thither, that he might have leiſure enough to prepare his Anſwers.
<note place="margin">He inſtitutes a religious proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> He alſo eſtabliſhed a ſort of Society or Fraternity, where they carried lighted Torches in their hands, with diverſe Ceremonies, that laſted three days. On the firſt, Proclamation was made as they do at <hi>Athens, If there be here any</hi> Epicurean, <hi>or</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>or impious perſon, who comes on purpoſe to ridicule our myſteries, let him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately withdraw: but let the faithful be initiated, and not loſe the opportunity.</hi> Then he marched at the head of them, crying aloud, <hi>Chriſtians be gone;</hi> and all the multitude an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Away Epicureans.</hi> After this they celebrated <hi>Latona</hi>'s lying in, with the birth of <hi>Apollo</hi> and the marriage of <hi>Coronis;</hi> all which was followed with the arrival of <hi>Aeſculapius.</hi> On the ſecond day was ſolemnized the nativity of <hi>Glycon,</hi> and on the third the Marriage of <hi>Podalirius</hi> and the Mother of our Prophet, and then the Torches were all lighted, from whence the whole Ceremony borrowed its name. There
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34162:12"/>were likewiſe repreſented the Amours of our Prophet and the Moon, of whom the Wife of <hi>Rutilianus</hi> was born, and he compoſed himſelf to ſleep in the midſt of the Ceremony like another <hi>Endimion.</hi> At the ſame time a handſom Lady deſcended down from a Machine who repreſented the Moon, She was Wife to the Deputies Steward, and had the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in her Husbands preſence to kiſs and embrace our holy Impoſtor, and perhaps the affair had been carried farther, if it had not been for the Company, for 'tis well known that they had no averſion one to the other.</p>
            <p> At another time he made his appearance in his Pontifical Habits,
<note place="margin">Our Sham Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet would have made a good Maſter of the ceremonies to the Pope.</note> keeping at firſt great ſilence, and then cried out all on the ſudden <hi>Io Glycon,</hi> to which a large Chorus of Muſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans anſwered <hi>Io Alexander,</hi> followed by the Heralds of the Country, who were huge luſty Clod pates, in Fantaſtic Garbs. All this while as the proceſſion paſſed along with Flambeaux, and many miſterious antick geſtures, he took care ever and anon to diſcover his golden thigh, which he did to Counterfeit <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and effected it, as I imagine, by the means of a gilt skin, that made a glittering, reflexion by the light of the Torches. This buſineſs raiſed a mighty debate between two Philoſophers, <hi>viz.</hi> whether he had not the Soul of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> as well as his Thigh, but it was referred to the deciſion of his Oracle, which anſwered that the Soul of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> aroſe and died from time to time, whereas that of our Prophet, was immortal, and of Divine extraction.</p>
            <p>Altho he forbid the love of Boys as damnable and deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able yet he commanded the Cities of <hi>Pontus</hi> and <hi>Paphlagenia</hi> to ſend him ſuch to conſult his Oracle, and ſing the Praiſes of his God.
<note place="margin">'Tis no new thing for the Prieſthood to preach agalnſt the things they recommend by their practice.</note> In perſuance of this Order they ſent him eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry third year Boys born of good Parentage, and the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt they could find, whom this Pious Letcher made uſe of in his ſecret Pleaſures. He had eſtabliſhed a pleaſant cuſtom, which was, that none ſhould preſume to kiſs him if they were above eighteen years old: by which politic he only kiſſed thoſe that were young, whom for this reaſon he was uſed to call his <hi>kiſſing Children.</hi> As for other People he he gave them his hand to kiſs.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34162:13"/>
            <p>Behold after what a prodigious manner he abuſed theſe poor believing wretches, who took it for a great favour to ſee him careſs their Wives and Children: Nay ſome of the women openly boaſted that they were with Child by him, and forced their Husbands to witneſs as much.
<note place="margin">The true reaſon why the women were always ſo fond of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtics.</note>But ſetting aſide ſuch ſtories, I will here relate to you a Dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the God and a Prieſt of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o,</hi> whoſe inclinations you'l be able to gueſs at by his anſwers, as I my ſelf did, who read the whole paſſage at his Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A pleſant Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue between a Prieſt and the Oracle.</note> Queſtion.<hi>Tell me,</hi> John Caſe, <hi>who art thou?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I am the new Dr. <hi>Saffold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Art thou Dr.</hi> Saffold <hi>himſelf, or ſome body elſe that reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not permitted to reveal theſe Miſteries.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many years wilt thou continue here to give Oracles near</hi> Ludgate?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> More than a dozen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where doſt thou intend to go after that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To <hi>White-Fryers,</hi> then to <hi>Moor-fields,</hi> to honour the Out-skirts of the Town with my preſenc.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are the Oracles of</hi> Gadbury, <hi>Dr.</hi> Partridge, <hi>and Poor</hi> Robin <hi>true Oracles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Don't deſire to know forbidden things.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall I drink when I go from hence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt Flip, then Cherry-brandy, next Sherry and Sugar, next Brandy and Gun-powder, and laſtly a Doſe of Liquid Brimſtone to fettle your Stomack for Eternity to prevent any farther curdling of Conſcience, or Paultry pukes of Grace:</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:34162:13"/>
            <p>This was the ſum and ſubſtance of the fine Converſation between them.
<note place="margin">Who put no great Faith in his Miracles.</note> But our Quack knowing this Prieſt to be a Friend of <hi>Lepidus,</hi> he muſt needs trump up an Oracle to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all future correſpondence between them, in which he preſended that <hi>Lepidus</hi> threatned to put him to a cruel death: For he feared <hi>Epicurus</hi> and his Followers, as being ſworn Enemies to his impoſtures, ſo that he employed all his efforts to get a poor <hi>Epicurean</hi> truſſed up, who had the hardineſs to reproach him, with cauſing ſeveral innocent perſons to be put to death by the means of his lying Oracle, which happened after this manner.</p>
            <p>He had adviſed a certain man of that Country,
<note place="margin">Here is a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimen of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion's Mercy.</note> to accuſe his Slaves before the Governor of that Province, as acceſſory to the death of his Son, who ſailing up the <hi>Nile,</hi> was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to go as far as the <hi>Indies,</hi> without ſaying a word of the matter to his People, whom he left behind him at <hi>Alexandria.</hi> Theſe Fellows bearing no news of their young Maſter, gave him for dead, and ſo returned home to his Father, who accuſed them, as I told you, before the Proconſul of <hi>Galatia,</hi> at the inſtigation of this Oracle, and had them hanged for it. Some time after the execution was over, and the poor Wretches diſpatched into another world, comes home the dead Son who juſtified their Innocence, but now there was no remedy for what was paſt. Our Prophet not being able to endure the many juſt reproaches that were made him upon this ſcore, commanded thoſe that were about him to ſtone the Accuſer, unleſs they were minded to be his Accomplices; and the Mob had moſt aſſuredly done as they were bidden, if one <hi>Demonſtratus</hi> who happened to be upon the ſpot had not immediately reſcued him. As for my ſelf, I ſhould not have complained much, had the buſineſs taken effect; for why the Devil ſhould a man of ſenſe hazard his life to undeceive a parcel of Sots that don't deſerve it.</p>
            <p>He did another thing, which occaſioned no leſs clamor. It was his fortune to light upon a book that contained the principal doctrines of <hi>Epicurus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In a fit of Zeal he ſentences an</hi> Epicurean <hi>book to the Flames.</hi>
               </note> 'Tis in my mind one of the nobleſt remainders of antiquity, and purges our Souls of its infirmities much better than all the Ceremonies of Purification;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34162:14"/>for it not only heals and cures us of our extravagant paſſions, but delivers us from all ſuperſtition, and thoſe vain fantoms that fright us out of our Senſes. Having found this book, as I have already told you; he publickly burnt it, after he had forged an Oracle to countenance the buſineſs, and threw the aſhes into the Sea. But now prepare to hear the moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent untruth that ever was uttered.</p>
            <p>As he had got his admiſſion into the Court, by the means and intereſt of his Son in-law <hi>Rutilianus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A true trimming Court Divine will never be in the wrong.</note> he ſent an Oracle to the Emperor <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> who was at that time making War in <hi>Germany,</hi> wherein he commanded him to throw two Lions into the <hi>Danube</hi> with ſeveral Ceremonies, giving him an aſſurance of an immediate Peace, which ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by a remarkable Victory. Theſe Lions croſſing the River were killed by the Enemy, and ſoon after the <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> defeated the <hi>Romans,</hi> who had like to have loſt <hi>Aquileia,</hi> after the total overthrow of Twenty Thouſand of their men. But this hardened Villain to ſave his Bacon made uſe of <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Artifice to <hi>Croeſus,</hi> pretending that he had rightly foretold a great Victory, but never declared the name of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror.</p>
            <p>Now vaſt Multitudes of People flocking to him from all parts, and the ſmalineſs of the City, where he lived, not being able to contain ſuch prodigious numbers, much leſs to feed them, he invented Night Oracles, for ſo the Beaſt named them, which he managed as follows.
<note place="margin">Our Prophet has more Strings to his Bow than one.</note> After he had received his Queſtions he went to ſleep, and gave out that he was informed in a Dream of the Anſwer he was to make, which was always either doubtful or obſcure eſpecially when the Letter was too accurately ſealed to be opened without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. In ſuch caſes he generally returned the firſt Anſwer that came into his Head, either becauſe ſuch a conduct looked moſt like that of other Oracles, or becauſe it brought him in the greateſt griſt to his Mill: for he had ſeveral Interpreters about him to explain theſe Night. Oracles, each of whom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents him yearly with a Talent by way of recompence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of receiving any appointment from him.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34162:14"/>
            <p>Sometimes when he had no body to conſult him, he forged new Oracles to amuſe the Sots,
<note place="margin">How ſtrangely be abuſes the credulity of the People.</note> as for inſtance this, which ſays, <hi>Search the Prentice in whom thou confideſt moſt, for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the injuries thou haſt done him, he carries a Pen Knife in his Pocket, and leſt thou ſhouldſt diſcover it, thy Wife</hi> Kate <hi>and He deſign to ſwear thee into a Plot, by the ſame token that thy maid</hi> Joan <hi>is an accomplice.</hi> Who is the <hi>Democritus</hi> that wou'd not have been impoſed upon, after ſo many circumſtances? but he was immediately laughed out of the trick after it was once diſcovered. If a Queſtion was put to him in a ſtrange Language, he deferred the Anſwer to gain time to return it in the ſame Tongue; and when he had no body to help him off at ſuch a pinch, he was obliged to make a vertue of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and anſwer it in his own, as once he did when he ſaid, <hi>Stranger return into thy own Country, for he that has ſent thee hither waas murdered yeſterday by</hi> John a Stiles, <hi>and the Aſſaſſinates are all in the</hi> Gazette.</p>
            <p>I muſt now beg leave to recount ſome of the Oracles, which he was pleaſed to communicate to my ſelf.
<note place="margin">Lucian <hi>puts the Doctor upon the Oracle.</hi>
               </note> One day when I had enquired of the God (and 'twas a queſtion not eaſy to be reſolved) whether his Prophet was in a milk dyet or no, he anſwered me in his hum drum way, <hi>Tom Thumb</hi> Son to <hi>William Thumb,</hi> and Nephew to <hi>Adoniram Thumb</hi> the Grocer has ſold himſelf to a Tobacco Plantation. At another time having writ the ſame demand in ſeveral Pillets, all which were brought to him from different places, that he might miſtruſt nothing, he ordered me in his Anſwer to viſit the Bagnio in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> and forbear Claret, having been deceived by the Fellow that brought him the Billet; who told him that I asked a Remedy againſt piſſing of Needles. Nevertheleſs my Queſtion was, who ſtood Godfather to the Monument. In another, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking the leaſt notice of the Monument or <hi>Fiſh-ſtreet</hi> hill, he very gravely forbad me to call at <hi>Putney,</hi> being in like manner bantered by the Footman who preſented him the Billet, and aſſured him that I only enquired which was the beſt way for me to return to back to <hi>Moreclack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I bethought my ſelf of ſeveral other inventions to diſcover his Roguery, as for inſtance, to put only one demand in a
<note place="margin">There are more ways to the VVood than one.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:34162:15"/>Billet, and to pay as if there were ſeveral tack'd together, for his cuſtom was to give you juſt ſo many Oracles as you paid Shillings, and theſe had no manner of relation either to themſelves, or to the Queſtion. Having therefore manifeſtly diſcovered the juggle, I uſed all my endeavors to diſengage <hi>Rutilianus</hi> from any alliance with him, which made the lying Bard conceive a mortal hatred againſt me, and he was not unmindful to quit ſcores with me as ſoon as he ſaw a fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity. For when <hi>Rutilianus</hi> conſulted the Oracle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me, he anſwered, <hi>That I loved young Boys, and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Pleaſures.</hi> I remember I went to ſee him once, having two Souldiers in my company which the Governour of the Province, who was my very good friend, ſent along with me, leſt he ſhould do me a miſchief. As ſoon as he heard of my arrival, he diſpatched one of his Servants to invite me to his houſe, and in appearance received me with great civility. Nevertheleſs I ſo perfectly hated him for his damn'd Villanies and Cheats, that when he gave me his hand to kiſs, I could not forbear biting it, and that with ſo good a Stomach, that 'tis ſtrange he did not ſet his Myrmidons upon me to teach me better manners, by knocking out my brains; and ſo much the rather, becauſe I called him by his name, without giving him the title of Doctor to uſher it in.</p>
            <p>To ſay the truth, this old Raſcal bore the affront with wonderful patience;
<note place="margin">It is not always convenient for a man to diſcover his deſigns.</note> he told me he had a mind to ſhow me that his God could calm the moſt outragious Spirits: After this, making ſigns for the company to withdraw, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of me for endeavouring to make a breach between him and <hi>Rutilianus;</hi> telling me I took very wrong meaſures to quarrel with the man who was in a capacity to make my Fortune when he pleaſed. I ſeemed to liſten very attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his diſcourſe, to ſave my ſelf from the danger that threatned me, and departed in very good terms from him, which ſtill more and more aſtoniſhed the ſtanders by.</p>
            <p>Reſolving at laſt to embark, he ſent me ſeveral preſents, furniſhed me with a Felucca and men to row her;
<note place="margin">Oh the great Bowels of your Pretenders to Santſhip!</note> which made me believe that he deſign'd to gain me over to his party by this extraordinary favour. When we were got far enough from any ſhore, I perceived the Bilot weeping, and diſputing it very earneſtly with the Sea-men. This alarm'd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34162:15"/>me with diſtruſt of my ſafety, and ſo much the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had but one of my Servants with me, having ſent back the reſt to <hi>Amaſtris</hi> with my Father. I enquired what was the occaſion of the diſpute? and he told me, That being now old, and having always behaved himſelf like an honeſt man, he was not willing in the laſt ſcene of his life to ſully all with a wicked action, nor expoſe his Wife and Children to divine vengeance. When I ſtill preſt him to tell me what was the matter, he confeſt that he had orders to throw me over board. Upon this information I deſired him to ſet me aſhore at the next Port; where meeting with ſome Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, who were going to carry their yearly Tribute to the Emperour, I told them my adventure, which made that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon them, that they gave me room in their Veſſel, and landed me ſafe at <hi>Amaſtris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Villain had ſerved me this Dog trick, I declared open War againſt him, and was upon the point of ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him before his betters, as ſeveral other Gentleme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were ready to do;
<note place="margin">Lucian <hi>reſolves to be even with him, but is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded.</hi>
               </note> but the Governour of the Province earneſtly deſired me to let the buſineſs fall; adding, that tho I ſhould diſcover never ſo many of his Impoſtures, yet ſo long as the Raſcal had <hi>Rutilianus</hi>'s ear, it would ſignifie juſt nothing; for whilſt he was in credit with a perſon of his quality, the Law would never reach him. This advice prevailed with us to deſiſt. But to purſue my Hiſtory: What an intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſolence was it in our Quack, to petition the Emperour to change the name of the City, and call it <hi>Ionopolis?</hi> Or who can ever forgive a Scoundrel of his infamous Character, for ordering Medals to be ſtampt, bearing the figure of a Serpent on one ſide, and his own on the reverſe, with the arms of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> and the Ax of <hi>Perſeus,</hi> from whom he pretends himſelf to be deſcended on the Mothers ſide?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſe Medals are to be ſeen in Dr.</hi> Spon<hi>'s</hi> xxi. <hi>Diſſertation.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, (for I am abominably weary with raking this Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill ſo long) he foretold that he ſhould dye by a Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clap, like <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> after the term of a hundred and fifty years;
<note place="margin">The miſerable end of this Juggler.</note> but for all his Predictions, he periſhed miſerably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had fully compleated ſeventy of them, of a naſty pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent Ulcer in his Leg, which ſeized upon all his lower parts, and filled him with innumerable vermin. At this time it was firſt known that our ſham Prophet was bald, when the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34162:16"/>Chyrurgeons applied Plaiſters to his Head, to aſſwage the pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Behold the Cataſtrophe of this Emperic, which was but a juſt puniſhment for his other crimes. He wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now but an Epitaph and a Succeſſor worthy of him; but I my ſelf dare pretend to Prophecy ſo far, as to affirm that he muſt be content to go without both, and that for the ſame reaſon: for as no Epitaph can poſſibly be made bad enough to be worthy of him, ſo no Villain now living can plead merit, that is, Villany enough to entitle him to his Mantle. Nature as well demands time to breathe after ſhe has form'd an accompliſh'd thorough pac'd Rogue, as after ſhe has made a perfect Hero. Perhaps ſome dozen ages hence, and in a diſtant Climate, a perſon may ariſe with all his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications and endowments;
<note place="margin">☞</note> but till then we muſt not expect ſuch a Phoenix: ſhe has exhauſted all her ſtore in our <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and muſt be allowed ſufficient time to recruit herſelf, before ſhe can afford to produce another.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Concluſion.</note>Thus, my dear <hi>Celſus,</hi> I have given you the abridgment of this Impoſtors Life; which I undertook partly to gratifie your Curioſity, and partly to diſabuſe ſome well meaning perſons, who have been impoſed upon by him in his life time. Tho it was a nauſeous employment, yet I was not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it either to your friendſhip, or the profound eſteem which I have of your probity; not to mention the greatneſs of your merits, and your love for truth, which are topics too bril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, to be handed in ſo inconſiderable and ſhort-liv'd a Paper as this.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34162:16"/>
            <head>To the Unknown Tranſlator, by a young Married Woman.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MOſt unſeen Sir, who e're you are,</l>
               <l>You've drawn a canting Quack ſo fair.</l>
               <l>So painted the Religious Creature,</l>
               <l>Shown every Lineament and Feature</l>
               <l>That as I am a breeding Woman,</l>
               <l>You've ſet me longing for ſome <hi>Salmon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should I miſcarry, troth it may be,</l>
               <l>The utter Ruine of my Baby.</l>
               <l>At leaſt ſome Fiſhes ſignature,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his Face, or Back for ſure.</l>
               <l>Which to prevint I went to hear him,</l>
               <l>But could not for the Crowd come near him.</l>
               <l>Some bid Money for the whole,</l>
               <l>I for the Tail-piece, or the Jole:</l>
               <l>But Middle-piece upon examen,</l>
               <l>Was found worth all the reſt o'th <hi>Salmon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Fiſh-wife for him agreat Stickler,</l>
               <l>('Tis thought by ſome the Quack did tickle her)</l>
               <l>Told me, ſhe was with him beyond Sea,</l>
               <l>Yet never did ſo fine a man ſee.</l>
               <l>I ask'd her where. She ſaid <hi>New-England,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And further than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Neighbors told me, that this Quack,</l>
               <l>Came home with Mermaid on his Back.</l>
               <l>And if't be true, all that we hear,</l>
               <l>She ſpawn'd at <hi>Graveſend</hi> her Cavere;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>This holy Siſter, was delivered of a Child at</hi> Graveſend.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Till Charge and Clamor 'gan to tire him,</l>
               <l>He parted with 's beloved <hi>Syren.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis Task too tedious to purſue,</l>
               <l>His Story longer—ſo adieu.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
